I'm a garbage man.
أنا رجل نفايات
And you might find it interesting that I became a garbage man,
وقد تجدون كوني رجل نفايات أمرٌ مثير للإهتمام
because I absolutely hate waste.
لأنني أكره تماماً الهدر
I hope, within the next 10 minutes,
أتمنى خلال الـ 10 دقائق التالية
to change the way you think
أن أغير طريقة تفكيركم
about a lot of the stuff in your life.
عن كثير من الأشياء في حياتكم
And I'd like to start at the very beginning.
وأريد أن أبدأ من البداية
Think back when you were just a kid.
عد بتفكيرك إلى الوراء قليلاً عندما كنت طفلاً
How did look at the stuff in your life?
كيف كنت تنظر إلى الأشياء في حياتك؟
Perhaps it was like these toddler rules:
ربما كانت نظرتك مثل قواعد الأطفال هذه:
It's my stuff if I saw it first.
إنها ملكي لأنني رأيتها أولاً
The entire pile is my stuff if I'm building something.
الكومة كلها ملكي إذا كنت أبني شيئاً
The more stuff that's mine, the better.
كلما كانت أشيائي أكثر كلما كان أفضل
And of course, it's your stuff if it's broken.
وبالطبع إنها أشيائك إذا كانت محطمة
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Well after spending about 20 years in the recycling industry,
بعد قضاء 20 سنة في صناعة إعادة التدوير
it's become pretty clear to me
أصبح واضحاً بالنسبة لي
that we don't necessarily leave these toddler rules behind
بأننا لا نترك بالضرورة قواعد الأطفال تلك وراءنا ولا نتجاوزها
as we develop into adults.
خلال نمونا إلى مرحلة البلوغ.
And let me tell you why I have that perspective.
ودعوني أخبركم لماذا أصبح لدي هذا المنظور
Because each and every day
لأنه في كل يوم
at our recycling plants around the world
في محطات التدوير لدينا في جميع أنحاء العالم
we handle about one million pounds
نتعامل مع نحو مليون رطل
of people's discarded stuff.
من الأشياء التي تخلص منها الناس
Now a million pounds a day sounds like a lot of stuff,
مليون رطل يومياً تبدو كأشياء كثيرة جداً
but it's a tiny drop of the durable goods
لكنها قطرة صغيرة من الأشياء المعمرة
that are disposed each and every year around the world --
والتي يتم التخلص منها في كل سنة حول العالم
well less than one percent.
يعني تمثل قرابة واحد بالمئة
In fact, the United Nations estimates
في الواقع، تشير تقديرات الأمم المتحدة
that there's about 85 billion pounds a year
بأن هنالك حوالي 95 بليون رطل سنوياً
of electronics waste
من النفايات الالكترونية
that gets discarded around the world each and every year --
والتي يتم التخلص منها حول العالم في كل سنة
and that's one of the most rapidly growing parts of our waste stream.
وهذه واحدة من الأجزاء ذات النمو الأكثر والأسرع من نفاياتنا
And if you throw in other durable goods like automobiles and so forth,
وإذا قمت برمي نفايات معمرة أخرى مثل السيارات وغيرها
that number well more than doubles.
سيزيد هذا الرقم إلى أكثر من الضعف
And of course, the more developed the country,
وبالطبع، كلما كانت الدولة متطورة أكثر
the bigger these mountains.
كلما زادت جبال النفايات
Now when you see these mountains,
والآن عندما ترى هذه الجبال
most people think of garbage.
أكثر الناس تراها على أنها مجرد نفايات
We see above-ground mines.
ولكن نحن نرى مناجم فوق الأرض
And the reason we see mines is because there's a lot of valuable raw materials
والسبب خلف رؤيتنا للمناجم هو أنه يوجد الكثير من المواد الخام ذات القيمة الكبيرة
that went into making all of this stuff in the first place.
والتي دخلت في تصنيع هذه الأشياء في الأساس
And it's becoming increasingly important
وقد أصبحت الحاجة ملحة بشكل كبير
that we figure out how to extract these raw materials
لإكتشاف طريقة نستطيع من خلالها استخلاص هذه المواد الخام
from these extremely complicated waste streams.
من سيل النفايات المعقد جداً
Because as we've heard all week at TED,
ولأننا كما سمعنا في تيد طوال الإسبوع
the world's getting to be a smaller place with more people in it
بأن العالم يصبح أصغر وأصغر بزيادة أعداد الناس فيه
who want more and more stuff.
تريد أشياء أكثر وأكثر
And of course, they want the toys and the tools
وبالطبع، هم يريدون الألعاب والأدوات
that many of us take for granted.
والتي تعتبر للكثير منا أمراً مفروغاً منه
And what goes into making those toys and tools
وما هي المواد التي تدخل في صنع هذه الألعاب والأدوات
that we use every single day?
والتي نستخدمها بشكل يومي؟
It's mostly many types of plastics and many types of metals.
هي في الغالب أنواع عديدة من البلاستيك والمعادن.
And the metals, we typically get
وهذه المعادن التي نحصل عليها عادة
from ore that we mine
من خام نستخرجه
in ever widening mines
من مناجم واسعة
and ever deepening mines around the world.
ومناجم عميقة في جميع أنحاء العالم
And the plastics, we get from oil,
والبلاستيك الذي نحصل عليه من النفط
which we go to more remote locations
والذي يجعلنا نذهب إلى أماكن بعيدة جدا
and drill ever deeper wells to extract.
ونحفر آبار عميقة جدا لاستخراجه
And these practices have
وهذه الممارسات تترتب عليها
significant economic and environmental implications
آثار اقتصادية وبيئية هامة
that we're already starting to see today.
والتي بدأنا نراها بالفعل اليوم
The good news is we are starting to recover materials from our end-of-life stuff
والخبر السار هو أننا بدأنا بإستعادة مواد من الأشياء المنتهية الصلاحية لدينا
and starting to recycle our end-of-life stuff,
وبدأنا بإعادة تدوير تلك الأشياء
particularly in regions of the world like here in Europe
خاصة في مناطق من العالم مثل هنا في أوروبا
that have recycling policies in place
والتي تمتلك سياسات إعادة تدوير معمول بها
that require that this stuff be recycled
والتي تتطلب إعادة تدوير هذه الأشياء
in a responsible manner.
بطريقة مسئولة
Most of what's extracted from our end-of-life stuff,
وغالبية المستخلص من أشياءنا منتهية الصلاحية
if it makes it to a recycler, are the metals.
تلك التي تصل إلى مرحلة إعادة التدوير هي المعادن
To put that in perspective --
ولوضع هذا في منظور
and I'm using steel as a proxy here for metals,
وسأستخدم الفولاذ هنا نيابة عن المعادن
because it's the most common metal --
لأنه المعدن الأكثر شيوعاً
if your stuff makes it to a recycler,
في حال وصلت أشياءك إلى مركز إعادة تدوير
probably over 90 percent of the metals
من المحتمل أن أكثر من 90% من المعادن
are going to be recovered and reused for another purpose.
ستسترجع وتستخدم في شيء آخر
Plastics are a whole other story:
ولكن البلاستيك هو حالة أخرى تماماً
well less than 10 percent are recovered.
فيتم إسترجاع أقل من 10%
In fact, it's more like five percent.
في الواقع، إنه أقرب إلى 5%
Most of it's incinerated or landfilled.
أكثرها يتم حرقها أو طمرها
Now most people think that's because plastics are a throw-away material,
والآن أكثر الناس تعتقد أن هذا بسبب كون البلاستيك مادة ترمى
have very little value.
وأنها ذات أهمية قليلة
But actually, plastics are several times more valuable than steel.
ولكن في الحقيقة، البلاستيك أكثر أهمية من الفولاذ بعدة مراحل
And there's more plastics produced and consumed
وهناك الكثير من البلاستيك الذي يتم إنتاجه واستخدامه
around the world on a volume basis
حول العالم على أكثر " حجمياً "
every year than steel.
من الفولاذ في كل سنه
So why is such a plentiful and valuable material
فلماذا مثل هذه المادة الوفيرة والقيمة
not recovered at anywhere near the rate
لا تسترد بأي شكل بالقرب من معدل
of the less valuable material?
استرجاع المواد الأقل قيمة؟
Well it's predominantly because
وهذا بالغالب بسبب
metals are very easy to recycle
أن إعادة تدوير المعادن سهل جداً وأيضاً فصلها
from other materials and from one another.
عن الأشياء الأخرى وعن بعضها البعض
They have very different densities.
فلديهم كثافة مختلفة جداً
They have different electrical and magnetic properties.
ولديهم خصائص إلكترونية ومغناطيسية مختلفة
And they even have different colors.
ولديهم كذلك ألوان مختلفة
So it's very easy for either humans or machines
ولذلك كان من السهل جداً للإنسان أو الآلات
to separate these metals
أن يقوموا بفصل هذه المعادن
from one another and from other materials.
عن بعضها البعض وعن المواد الأخرى
Plastics have overlapping densities over a very narrow range.
ولكن أنواع البلاستيك لديها كثافة تتداخل مع بعضها البعض على نطاق ضيق جداً
They have either identical or very similar
ولديهم إما متطابقة أو متشابهة جداً
electrical and magnetic properties.
خصائص الكترونية ومغناطيسية
And any plastic can be any color,
وأيضاً اي بلاستيك يمكن أن يمتلك أي لون
as you probably well know.
كما تعرفون جيدا
So the traditional ways of separating materials
ولذلك فإن الطريقة الإعتيادية لفصل المواد
just simply don't work for plastics.
غير مجدية مع المواد البلاستيكية ببساطة
Another consequence of metals being so easy to recycle by humans
ونتيجة أخرى لكون المعادن سهلة إعادة التدوير جداً من قبل الإنسان
is that a lot of our stuff from the developed world --
هي أن كثير من أشياءنا في العالم المتطور
and sadly to say, particularly from the United States,
ويحزنني القول خاصة في الولايات المتحدة
where we don't have any recycling policies in place like here in Europe --
حيث لا يوجد لدينا سياسات إعادة تدوير تعمل بشكل فعّال كما هو الحال هنا في أوروبا
finds its way to developing countries
تجد طريقها إلى الدول الناشئة
for low-cost recycling.
لعمليات إعادة تدوير رخيصة
People, for as little as a dollar a day, pick through our stuff.
حيث يقوم الناس بالنبش في أشياءنا مقابل أقل من دولار يومياً
They extract what they can, which is mostly the metals --
فيقومون باستخراج ما يمكنهم استخراجه ويكون ذلك غالبا من المعادن
circuit boards and so forth --
لوح الدارات وما إلى ذلك
and they leave behind mostly what they can't recover,
ويتركون وراءهم في الغالب ما لا يمكنهم اصلاحه
which is, again, mostly the plastics.
وهو في الغالب البلاستيك
Or they burn the plastics to get to the metals
أو يقومون بإحراق البلاستيك للوصول إلى المعادن
in burn houses like you see here.
في منازل حرق كما ترون هنا
And they extract the metals by hand.
ويقومون بفصل المعادن بيديهم
Now while this may be the low-economic-cost solution,
في حين قد يكون هذا حلاً ذا تكلفة إقتصادية منخفضة
this is certainly not the low-environmental
فهو بالتأكيد ليس منخفض التكلفة بيئياً
or human health-and-safety solution.
أو على مستوى صحة وسلامة الإنسان
I call this environmental arbitrage.
أسمي هذا موازنة بيئية
And it's not fair, it's not safe
وهو ليس حل عدل ولا آمن
and it's not sustainable.
وأيضاً ليس مستدام
Now because the plastics are so plentiful --
والآن بما أن البلاستيك وفير جداً
and by the way,
وبالمناسبة
those other methods don't lead to the recovery of plastics, obviously --
تلك الطرق الأخرى لا تسترد البلاستيك كما هو واضح
but people do try to recover the plastics.
ولكن الناس يحاولون إسترداده
This is just one example.
وهذا مثال واحد فقط
This is a photo I took standing on the rooftops
هذه صورة إلتقطتها حينما كنت واقفاً على سطح أحد المنازل
of one of the largest slums in the world in Mumbai, India.
لواحدة من أكبر الأحياء الفقيرة في العالم في مدينة بومباي بالهند
They store the plastics on the roofs.
فهم يخزنون البلاستيك على السطوح
They bring them below those roofs into small workshops like these,
ويجلبونها للأسفل لورش صغيرة كهذه
and people try very hard to separate the plastics,
ويحاول الناس جاهدون فصل البلاستيك
by color, by shape, by feel,
على حسب اللون والشكل والملمس
by any technique they can.
بأي طريقة يستطيعون
And sometimes they'll resort to what's known as the "burn and sniff" technique
وفي بعض الأحيان يلجأون إلى تقنية "الحرق والشم"
where they'll burn the plastic and smell the fumes
حيث يقومون بحرق البلاستيك وشم الدخان
to try to determine the type of plastic.
في محاولة لتحديد نوع البلاستيك
None of these techniques result in any amount of recycling
ولا ينتج عن أي تقنية من هذه التقنيات أي قدر من إعادة التدوير
in any significant way.
بأي طريقة تذكر
And by the way,
على فكرة
please don't try this technique at home.
رجاءا لا تجربوا هذه التقنية في منازلكم
So what are we to do about this space-age material,
فإذاً ما الذي يمكننا فعله تجاه هذه المواد المعمرة
at least what we used to call a space-aged material, these plastics?
أو على الأقل ما كنا نسميه المواد المعمرة ، هذه المواد البلاستيكية؟
Well I certainly believe that it's far too valuable and far too abundant
حسناً أنا اؤمن بكل تأكيد بأنها ذات قيمة كبيرة جداً ووفيرة جدا
to keep putting back in the ground
من أن نستمر بإرجاعها إلى الأرض
or certainly send up in smoke.
أو أن نرسلها إلى أعلى بالدخان
So about 20 years ago, I literally started in my garage tinkering around,
قمت قبل قرابة الـ 20 سنة بالبدء في مرأبي بترقيع الأشياء
trying to figure out how to separate
محاولاً بجهد لمعرفة كيفية فصل
these very similar materials from each other,
هذه المواد المتشابهة جداً
and eventually enlisted a lot of my friends,
وبالنهاية قمت بتوظيف الكثير من أصدقائي
in the mining world actually, and in the plastics world,
في عالم التنقيب وفي عالم البلاستيك
and we started going around to mining laboratories around the world.
وبدأنا بالإلتفاف حول مختبرات التنقيب في جميع أنحاء العالم
Because after all, we're doing above-ground mining.
وذلك لأننا في النهاية نقوم بالتنقيب فوق الأرض
And we eventually broke the code.
وفي النهاية قمنا بفك الشفرة
This is the last frontier of recycling.
هذه هي الحدود الأخيرة لإعادة التدوير
It's the last major material
إنها المادة الرئيسية الأخيرة
to be recovered in any significant amount on the Earth.
لإستعادتها بأي كمية تذكر على الأرض
And we finally figured out how to do it.
واستطعنا أخيراً أكتشاف كيفية فعل ذلك
And in the process, we started recreating
وخلال هذه العملية بدأنا في إعادة
how the plastics industry makes plastics.
كيفية قيام مصانع البلاستيك بصنع البلاستيك
The traditional way to make plastics
الطريقة التقليدية لصنع البلاستيك
is with oil or petrochemicals.
هي بإستخدام النفط أو البتروكيماويات
You breakdown the molecules, you recombine them in very specific ways,
حيث تقوم بتفكيك الجزيئات وإعادة تركيبها بطريقة محددة للغاية
to make all the wonderful plastics that we enjoy each and every day.
لصنع كل هذا البلاستيك الرائع الذي نتمتع به في كل يوم
We said, there's got to be a more sustainable way to make plastics.
فقلنا لا بد أن يكون هناك طريقة محتملة لصنع البلاستيك
And not just sustainable from an environmental standpoint,
ليس فقط محتملة من ناحية البيئة فقط
sustainable from an economic standpoint as well.
ولكن من ناحية إقتصادية أيضاً
Well a good place to start is with waste.
وأفضل طريقة للبدء هي النفايات
It certainly doesn't cost as much as oil,
والتي بالتأكيد لا تكلف بقدر النفط
and it's plentiful,
وهي وفيرة أيضا
as I hope that you've been able to see from the photographs.
وأتمنى أنكم استطعتوا أن تروا ذلك من خلال الصور
And because we're not breaking down the plastic into molecules
ولأننا لن نقوم بتفكيك البلاستيك إلى جزيئات
and recombining them,
ونعيد تركيبها
we're using a mining approach to extract the materials.
سنستخدم نهج التنقيب لإستخراج المواد
We have significantly lower capital costs
نحن نملك تكاليف رأسمالية منخفضة بشكل واضح
in our plant equipment.
في معدات محطتنا
We have enormous energy savings.
كما لدينا توفير هائل للطاقة
I don't know how many other projects on the planet right now
لا أعلم كم من المشاريع الأخرى في العالم الآن
can save 80 to 90 percent of the energy
والتي تستطيع أن توفر من 80 إلى 90 بالمية من الطاقة
compared to making something the traditional way.
مقارنة بصناعة شيء بالطريقة التقليدية
And instead of plopping down several hundred million dollars
وبدلاً من اسراف مئات المليوات من الدولارات
to build a chemical plant
لبناء مصنع كيميائي
that will only make one type of plastic for its entire life,
يقوم بصنع نوع واحد من البلاستيك طيلة حياته
our plants can make any type of plastic we feed them.
مصانعنا ستقوم بصنع أي نوع من البلاستيك نطعمها إياه
And we make a drop-in replacement
ونقوم بإستبدال بسيط
for that plastic that's made from petrochemicals.
للبلاستيك المصنوع من البتروكيماويات
Our customers get to enjoy
فيستمتع زباءننا
huge CO2 savings.
بتوفير ثنائي أكسيد الكربون بشكل هائل
They get to close the loop with their products.
ويصبح بإستطاعتهم إغلاق الحلقة مع منتجاتهم
And they get to make more sustainable products.
وبذلك يستطيعون صنع منتجات اكثر تحمل وبقاء
In the short time period I have,
وفي الوقت القصير المتبقي الآن
I want to show you a little bit of a sense about how we do this.
أريد أن اعرض عليكم بشكل مبسط عن كيفية قيامنا بهذا
It starts with metal recyclers who shred our stuff into very small bits.
تبدأ العملية من معيدي تدوير المعادن الذين يقومون بتقطيع أشياءنا لقطع صغيرة
They recover the metals
ويستعيدون المعادن
and leave behind what's called shredder residue -- it's their waste --
ويتركون ما يسمى ببقايا التقطيع -- مخلفاتهم --
a very complex mixture of materials,
وهو مزيج معقد جداً من المواد
but predominantly plastics.
ولكن في الغالب بلاستيك
We take out the things that aren't plastics,
فنقوم نحن بإبعاد المواد غير البلاستيكية
such as the metals they missed, carpeting, foam, rubber,
كالمعادن التي لم ينتبهوا لها والسجاد والرغوة والمطاط
wood, glass, paper, you name it.
والخشب والزجاج والورق وأي شيء آخر يخطر على بالك
Even an occasional dead animal, unfortunately.
وحتى في بعض الحالات تكون حيوانات ميتة للأسف
And it goes in the first part of our process here, which is more like traditional recycling.
وبعد ذلك يدخل البلاستيك في أول جزء من عمليتنا والتي تشبه عملية إعادة التدوير التقليدية
We're sieving the material, we're using magnets,
نحن نقوم بنخل المواد ونستخدم المغناطيس
we're using air classification.
وأيضا نستخدم تصنيف الهواء
It looks like the Willy Wonka factory at this point.
إنه أشبه بمصنع ويلي وونكا في هذه النقطة
At the end of this process, we have a mixed plastic composite:
ونحصل في نهاية هذه العملية على مركب من البلاستيك الممزوج
many different types of plastics
أنواع كثيرة من البلاستيك
and many different grades of plastics.
ودرجات كثيرة من البلاستيك
This goes into the more sophisticated part of our process,
ويدخل هذا المزيج بالجزء الأكثر تطوراً من عمليتنا
and the really hard work, multi-step separation process begins.
والاكثر صعوبة وتبدأ عملية الفصل المتعددة الخطوات
We grind the plastic down to about the size of your small fingernail.
نقوم بطحن البلاستيك إلى حوالي حجم ظفرك الصغير
We use a very highly automated process
نستخدم عملية آلية عالية جدا
to sort those plastics,
لفرز تلك المواد البلاستيكية
not only by type, but by grade.
ليس بحسب النوع فقط بل الدرجة أيضا
And out the end of that part of the process
وفي نهاية هذا الجزء من العملية
come little flakes of plastic:
نحصل على رقائق صغيرة من البلاستيك
one type, one grade.
نوع واحد ودرجة واحدة
We then use optical sorting to color sort this material.
ومن ثم نستخدم الفرز الضوئي لفرز هذه المواد بالألوان
We blend it in 50,000-lb. blending silos.
ونمزجها في 50،000 رطل من مزيج الصوامع
We push that material to extruders where we melt it,
ونقوم بدفع هذه المواد إلى البثوق حيث نقوم بإذابتها
push it through small die holes,
ندفعها من خلال ثقوب صغيرة
make spaghetti-like plastic strands.
صانعين بذلك خيوط بلاستيك تشبة السباغيتي
And we chop those strands
ونقوم بتقطيع هذه الخيوط
into what are called pellets.
إلى ما يسمى بالكريات
And this becomes the currency of the plastics industry.
وتصبح هذه العملة في صناعة البلاستيك
This is the same material
هذه هي نفس المواد
that you would get from oil.
التي تحصل عليها من النفط
And today,
واليوم
we're producing it from your old stuff,
نحن ننتجها من اشياءك القديمة
and it's going right back into your new stuff.
وتعود ثانية في أشياءك الجديدة
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
So now, instead of your stuff ending up
والآن، بدلاً من أن ينتهي المطاف بأشياءك
on a hillside in a developing country
ملقاة على أحد الهضاب في دولة نامية
or literally going up in smoke,
أو تتطاير حرفيا مع الدخان
you can find your old stuff
بإمكانك إيجاد أشياءك القديمة
back on top of your desk in new products,
على طاولتك مرة أخرى على شكل منتجات جديدة
in your office,
في مكتبك
or back at work in your home.
في العمل أو المنزل
And these are just a few examples
وهذه أمثلة قليلة فقط
of companies that are buying our plastic,
عن الشركات التي تشتري البلاستيك الخاص بنا
replacing virgin plastic,
عوضاً عن البلاستيك الأولي
to make their new products.
لصنع منتجاتهم الجديدة
So I hope I've changed the way you look at
أتمنى أن أكون قد غيرت نظرتكم عن
at least some of the stuff in your life.
على الأقل بعض الأشياء في حياتكم
We took our clues from mother nature.
أخذنا أدلتنا من الطبيعة الأم
Mother nature wastes very little,
فالطبيعة الأم تهدر القليل فقط
reuses practically everything.
وتعيد استخدام كل شيء تقريبا
And I hope that you stop looking at yourself as a consumer --
وأتمنى أن تتوفقوا عن النظر إلى أنفسكم كمستهلكين
that's a label I've always hated my entire life --
هذه علامة لطالما كرهتها طوال حياتي
and think of yourself as just using resources in one form,
وأنظر إلى نفسك فقط كمستخدم للموارد بشكل واحد
until they can be transformed to another form
حتى يكون بإمكانها التحول لشكل آخر
for another use later in time.
لإستخدام آخر في وقت لاحق
And finally, I hope you agree with me
وأخيراً، أتمنى أن تتفقوا معي
to change that last toddler rule just a little bit
لتغيير قاعدة الأطفال السابقة قليلاً
to: "If it's broken, it's my stuff."
إلى: "إذا كانت مكسورة فهي ملكي"
Thank you for your time.
شكراً لكم على وقتكم
(Applause)
(تصفيق)